A Guide to the John Hook Records, 1763-1829
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
John Hook Records, 1763-1829
Library of Virginia
22174
0.575 cubic feet
John Hook
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased in June 1927 except negative photostats made from manuscripts lent to the library by Felix Hargrett in October 1943.
Alternative Form Available
Letter books, 1763-1772, 1774-1784, also available on microfilm (Miscellaneous reel 642).
Biographical Information
John Hook (1746-1808) was the son of Henry Hook, a manufacturer of Glasgow, Scotland. John Hook arrived in the United States from Scotland in 1858. He married Elizabeth Smith of Goochland County circa 1772. They then settled in New London, Bedford County, where he kept a store until 1784, when he moved to Halesford, Franklin County. Hook was a party in a number of lawsuits, the most notable being the sequestration proceedings brought against him by Richmond merchant and former partner David Ross.
Scope and Content
Records, 1763-1829, of John Hook (1746-1808), a merchant of Bedford and Franklin Counties, Virginia. Includes three letter book volumes, 1 August 1763-28 May 1772; 1 June 1772-May 1774; 30 July 1774-16 April 1784, containing information on Hook's mercantile activities and partnerships, analyses of trade opportunities, and dealings with several Scottish merchants prominent in colonial Virginia. Correspondence between Hook and David Ross (ca. 1739-1817) also appears in the letter books along with letters from and to other members of the Hook family. This collection also includes correspondence, 1772-1809, 1829, and n.d., both to and from John Hook concerning his business affairs and lawsuits stemming from his business dealings. There also are separate series containing legal files pertaining to David Ross' lawsuits and a building plan for a store in New London, Bedford County, Virginia.
Arrangement
Arranged into the following four series: I. Letter books, 1763-1784; II. Correspondence, 1772-1808, 1829; III. Legal Files, 1775-1809, and n.d.; and IV. Building Plan, 1772.
Contents List
- Letterbooks, 1763-1784 (Box 1-2)
  Includes three letter book volumes, 1 August 1763-28 May 1772; 1 June 1772-May 1774; 30 July 1774-16 April 1784, containing information on Hook's mercantile activities and partnerships, analyses of trade opportunities, and dealings with several Scottish merchants prominent in colonial Virginia.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Letterbook, 1 August 1763-28 May 1772, 1 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Letterbook, 1 June 1772-14 May 1774, 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letterbook, 30 July 1774-16 April 1784, 3 (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
- Correspondence, 1772-1808, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
  Includes letters both to and from John Hook. Topics include prices of goods, trade and market conditions, military operations during the Revolutionary War, and the progress of the legal suits to which Hook was a party. Principal correspondents are Edmund Randolph, David Ross, and Andrew Lewis. This is correspondence that was not bound into letterbooks, as is the case with Series I.
  - Letter. David Ross, Richmond, Virginia, to John Hook, Bedford Courthouse, Bedford County, Virginia, 10 February 1772, 4; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. David Ross, Petersburg, Virginia, to John Hook, Bedford Courthouse, Bedford County, Virginia, 10 March 1772, 5; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. David Ross, Petersburg, Virginia, to John Hook, Bedford Courthouse, Bedford County, Virginia, 11 March 1772, 6; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. David Ross, Petersburg, Virginia, to John Hook, Bedford Courthouse, Bedford County, Virginia, 23 March 1772, 7; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. David Ross, Richmond, Virginia, to John Hook, Bedford Courthouse, Bedford County, Virginia, 5 May 1772, 8; 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. David Ross, Richmond, Virginia, to John Hook, Bedford Courthouse, Bedford County, Virginia, 4 June 1772, 9; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. David Ross, Petersburg, Virginia, to John Hook, Bedford Courthouse, Bedford County, Virginia, 22 April 1773, 10; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. David Ross, Petersburg, Virginia, to John Hook, New London, Bedford County, Virginia, 4 May 1773, 11; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. David Ross to John Hook, New London, Bedford County, Virginia, 19 February 1776, 12; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. David Ross, Oxford Iron Works, Bedford County, Virginia, to John Hook, New London, Bedford County, Virginia, October 1776, 13; 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. David Ross, Petersburg, Virginia, to John Hook, New London, Bedford County, Virginia, 30 October 1776, 14; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. David Ross, Oxford Iron Works, Bedford County, Virginia, to John Hook, New London, Bedford County, Virginia, 30 November 1776, 15; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. James Holliday, Wincheter, Virginia, to John Hook, New London, Bedford County, Virginia, 6 July 1778, 16; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. David Ross, Petersburg, Virginia, to John Hook, New London, Bedford County, Virginia, 21 July 1778, 17; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. David Ross, Petersburg, Virginia, to John Hook, New London, Bedford County, Virginia, 23 August 1778, 18; 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. David Ross, Petersburg, Virginia, to Alexander Baine, Fort Lewis, Virginia, 2 June 1780, 19; 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. John Hook, Manchester, Virginia, to William Smith, Franklin County, Virginia, 22 October 1792, 20; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. John Hook, Hailsford, Franklin County, Virginia, to Philemon Smith, 1 June 1793, 21; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. John Hook, Richmond, Virginia, to William Smith, Franklin County, Virginia, 7 November 1796, 22; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. John Hook, Hailsford, Franklin County, Virginia, to William S. Crawford, Amherst County, Virginia, 16 March 1800, 23; 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. Cornelius Pate, Big Lick, Botetourt County, Virginia, to John Hook, Hailsford, Frankling County, Virginia, 8 January 1802, 24; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. William M. Hening, Charlottesville, Virginia, to John Hook, Hailsford, Franklin County, Virginia, 19 March 1802, 25; 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. Edmund Randolph, Richmond, Virginia, to John Hook, Hailsford, Franklin County, Virginia, 17 March 1803, 26; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. Andrew Lewis, Richmond, Virginia, to John Hook, Franklin County, Virginia, 24 December 1805, 27; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. Andrew Lewis, Liberty, Bedford County, Virginia, to John Hook, Franklin County, Virginia, 10 February 1806, 28; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. John Hook, Jr., Lynchburg, Virginia, to John Hook, Hailsford, Franklin County, Virginia, 10 October 1806, 29; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. Andrew Lewis, Richmond, Virginia, to John Hook, Franklin County, Virginia, 22 December 1806, 30; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. W. A. Burwell, Washington, D. C., to John Hook, Liberty, Bedford County, Virginia, 4 January 1807, 31; 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. John Hook, Hailsford, Franklin County, Virginia, to Alexander Smith, Wythe County (?), Virginia, 2 March 1807, 32; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. John Hook, Richmond, Virginia, to Bowker Preston, Hailsford, Franklin County, Virginia, 12 June 1807, 33; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. Edmund Randolph to John Hook, Franklin County, Virginia, 20 February 1808, 34; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. John Hook to Patrick Hendren, 11 June 1808, 35; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. William Wirt, Richmond, Virginia, to John Hook, 28 June 1808, 36; 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. Philip Norborne Nicholas, Richmond, Virginia, to John Hook, Richmond, Virginia, 4 August 1808, 37; 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. Edmund Randolph, Spring Farm, Virginia, to John Hook, 18 September 1808, 38; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. John Hook to David Ross, 2 October 1808, 39; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. Peachy R. Gilmer, Liberty, Bedford County, Virginia, to Bowker Preston, Goose Creek, Virginia (?), 17 November 1829, 40; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Legal Files, 1775-1809 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  Principally contains the non-correspondence files pertaining to John Hook's lawsuits and legal affairs. Of note are documents concerning charges brought against Hook by the Bedford County Committee of Safety as an enemy to the Revolution. A letter from Hook addressing the charges along with his subsequent loyalty oath also are included.
  Arranged chronologically. Non-dated items arranged alphabetically at the end of the series.
  - Resolution of Bedford County Committee of Safety in re: John Hook, 23 May 1775, 41; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Answer of John Hook to charges of Charles Lynch, June 1775, 42; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. John Hook, New London, Bedford County, Virginia, to Bedford County Committee of Safety, 17 June 1775, 43; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Memorandum of Bedford County Committee of Safety in re: John Hook, 26 June 1775, 44; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Memorandum of Bedford County Committee of Safety, 1776, 45; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Memorandum in re: William Ray and Robert Griffith, October-November 1776, 46; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Complaint of John Hook against Colonel William Mead, et. al., 18 January 1777, 47; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Release of John Hook from Public Goal, 19 January 1777, 48; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Oath certificate of Samuel Hairston, 10 October 1777, 49; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Certification of Bourne Price in re: payment for services to John Chaplin, 17 November 1783, 50; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Declaration by Patrick Henry in suit John Calloway v. John Thompson, 1789, 51; 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Answer of John Hook in suit David Ross v. John Hook, 20 August 1801, 52; 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Deposition of Stephen Smith in suit David Ross v. John Hook, 14 June 1808, 53; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lawsuit receipt of James Graham, February 1809, 54; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Declaration by Edmund Randolph in suit John Hook v. Swinfield Hill and Company, n.d., 55; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Declaration in the suit John Hook v. David Ross, n.d., 56; 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Building Plan, 1772 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  This is a copy of a building plan for a store to be erected in New London, Bedford County, Virginia.